Every body that has a temperature radiates
energy.
How much energy does our sun radiate and how
much of it reaches us on earth?
How much energy does the Earth actually radiate
into space?
And what is the surface temperature of our
sun?
These and similar questions can be answered
by the Stefan-Boltzmann law.
This law describes the relationship between
the temperature T of a body and its radiant
power P.
The surface area A of the body also influences
the radiant power.
The Stefan-Boltzmann law is "P is equal to
sigma times A times T to the power of four"
Here, "sigma" is the Stefan-Boltzmann constant
with the value "five point six seven times
ten to the power of minus 8, joules per meter
squared times Kelvin to the power of four,
times second".
This is a constant that has an exact value
that only depends on other physical constants,
namely the Boltzmann constant, the Planck
constant and the speed of light.
What exactly is the radiant power P?
It indicates how much energy per second the
surface of the body radiates.
The unit of radiant power is watt, or joule
per second.
In addition, the Stefan-Boltzmann law only
applies to black bodies or bodies that come
close to a black body.
However, the term black has nothing to do
with the color of the body.
The sun, for example, is a nearly black body,
although, as you know, it is not black.
A black body absorbs all the radiation that
hits it.
It does not reflect any radiation and does
not allow any radiation to pass through.
The Stefan-Boltzmann law shows how much the
radiated energy depends on the temperature.
Doubling the surface temperature of the sun
would result in 16 times more solar energy
reaching the earth.
Let's take an example of how to determine
the temperature of the sun using the Stefan-Boltzmann
law.
We can deduce the total amount of energy emitted
by the sun from the energy we receive from
the sun.
The sun emits a power of "three point eight
times ten to the power of twenty-six joules
per second.
The radius of the sun is "six point nine six,
times ten to the power of eight meters".
Let's assume that the sun is not flat, but
spherical.
We can therefore use the formula for the surface
area of a sphere to determine the surface
area of the sun: "A is equal to four pi times
r squared".
Let's rearrange the Stefan-Boltzmann law with
respect to the temperature T and insert the
surface area formula.
If we now insert the radiant power, the Stefan-Boltzmann
constant and the solar radius, we get "five
thousand seven hundred sixty Kelvin" as the
surface temperature of the sun.
This corresponds to "six thousand thirty-three
degrees Celsius".